Christ mss., 2001-2006 LMC 2250
Lilly Library
Christ mss.
1967-2007
Lilly Library
Christ, Ronald J.
LMC 2250
3.75 linear feet 3 boxes
1 award
The Christ mss. 1967-2007, consists primarily of notes and drafts of translations by Professor Emeritus of English Ronald Christ. In addition, it contains collected papers from fellow authors and translators Helen Lane and Charles Greenleaf Bell.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Ronald Christ has published numerous articles on art and literature in addition to his work as a literary translator. He founded Lumen Books as an outlet for architectural and literary writing, especially in translation, and in 1998 was awarded the Eugene M. Kayden National Translation Award for his translation of Eltit's E. Luminata. Christ has also served as the president of PEN New Mexico. Christ enjoyed close friendships and working relationships with many authors and translators, most notably Helen Lane and Charles Greenleaf Bell, the latter of which Christ helped to publish an autobiography.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into five series: Translations, Additions, Professional Files, Helen Lane, and Charles Greenleaf Bell. Translations is further arranged by author subseries and Additions consists of one subseries: Translations, which is arranged alphabetically by author.
Scope and Content Note
Both the Translations and Additions series consist of typescripts, proofs, manuscripts, drafts, notes, corrections, and correspondence related to works translated by Christ. Professional Files are revisions Christ did for colleagues, various correspondence, and reviews of Christ's work as well as colleagues. The Helen Lane series is primarily Lane's papers or Christ's papers about Lane, including her translation work and correspondence at the time of her death. Lastly, the Charles Greenleaf Bell series are papers and correspondence concerning Christ's colleague and friend.
Related Material
See Bell mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Also acquired with books.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 2013
Literature--translating; Correspondence; Christ, Ronald J.; Bell, Charles G. (Charles Greenleaf), 1916-2010; Lumen books; Lane, Helen; Eugene M. Kayden national translation award
- I. TRANSLATIONS
  - Diamela, Eltit (Box 1)
    - Digital barking, typescript in Portuguese, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Digital barking, typescript in English, undated (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes (Los vigilantes), published book in Spanish with CD-ROM, Ronald Christ's working copy, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes, background materials, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes, Spanish text with notes, undated (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes, draft and queries, 2002; (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes, draft with notes, undated (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes, corrections with notes, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes, late draft (incomplete) with notes, undated (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes, final draft, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes, draft with queries and revisions, undated (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes, proof, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes, intermediate proofs with notes, undated (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes, final proof with notes, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Custody of the eyes, proof with final corrections, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Garavito, Fernando
    - Exercises in solitude, typescripts in Spanish and English with notes, 2004 (Box 1)
    - On writing and exile, typescripts in Spanish and English with notes, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence concerning translations, November 2004 (Box 1)
  - Ibargüengoitia, Jorge
    - Correspondence between Ronald Christ and colleagues seeking translation advice, August 2005 (Box 1)
    - Kill the lion, fourth draft with correspondence, July 2005 (Box 1)
    - Kill the lion, fourth draft with corrections, July 2005 (Box 1)
    - Kill the lion, final draft with corrections, July 2005; (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Kill the lion, final draft with revisions by Barbara Riley, August 2005; (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Kill the lion, CD-ROM, undated (Box 1)
  - Kodama, Maria
    - The dinosaur, first draft, corrections, January 2006 (Box 1)
- II. ADDITIONS
  - Translations (Box 2)
    - Altamirano, Ignacio Manuel, El Zarco correspondence, 2003-2007 (Box 2)
    - Altamirano, Ignacio Manuel, El Zarco photocopy of book in Spanish with notes, undated (Box 2)
    - Altamirano, Ignacio Manuel, El Zarco draft of an earlier translation with notes, undated (Box 2)
    - Altamirano, Ignacio Manuel, El Zarco introduction corrections with correspondence, September 2006 (Box 2)
    - Altamirano, Ignacio Manuel, El Zarco drafts with corrections, 2006; (7 folders) (Box 2)
    - ArtsCanada, correspondence with photographs, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - Cahill, Christopher correspondence and proofs, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Eltit, Diamela, correspondence, 1995-2006 (Box 2)
    - Garavito, Fernando, Las vacas volando intentos y ensayos draft, 2004; (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Garavito, Fernando, correspondence, 2004-2005; (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Kocbek, Edward, correspondence and draft with corrections, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Kodama, Maria, The Dinosaur draft with corrections, undated (Box 2)
    - Maruane, Lina, Razor Blades Spanish text, drafts, author's comments, corrections, 2006 (Box 2)
    - Pombo, Alvaro, Contra Natura correspondence, 2007 (Box 2)
    - Puig, Manuel, 1985; (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Sarduy, Severo, Pajaros de la playa correspondence and publisher agreements, 1997-2003 (Box 2)
    - Thida, Ma correspondence, corrections, 2005 (Box 2)
    - Walsh, Rodolfo, That woman, 2006 (Box 2)
    - West, Paul, The immensity of the here and now review, 2003 (Box 2)
    - West, Paul, correspondence, 1982-2007; (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - West, Paul, The shadow factory reviews, 2005 (Box 3)
    - West, Paul, The shadow factory reviews and correspondence, 2007 (Box 3)
    - West, Paul, The shadow factory draft with corrections, November 2007 (Box 3)
    - West, Paul, The shadow factory corrections, November 2007 (Box 3)
    - West, Paul, The shadow factory draft spiral bound, undated (Box 3)
    - West, Paul, Excerpts from publications presented from West to Christ, 1967-1977 (Box 3)
    - West, Paul, Miscellaneous, 1984-1992 (Box 3)
    - Research for Spanish translations, 2007 (Box 3)
- III. PROFESSIONAL FILES
  - Carol Maier's students' translations of Fernando Garavito revisions, May 2005 (Box 3)
  - Millennial harvest: collected poems of Charles bell revisions, July 2001 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1996-2007 (Box 3)
  - Victoria Ocampo translated by Karen Phillips revisions, undated (Box 3)
  - Reviews by Ronald Christ, 2001-2003 (Box 3)
  - General correspondence, 1997-2007 (Box 3)
  - Carol Maier interview with Ronald Christ, 1995 (Box 3)
- IV. HELEN LANE
  - Translation Review, number 5, "An interview with Helen R. Lane" by Ronald Christ, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Helen Lane's translation of Ricardo Palma, Peruvian traditions, Spanish copy with notes, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Reviews of Helen Lane's translation of Augusto Roa Bastos, I the supreme, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Helen Lane's file containing reviews, CV, and queries on Duele el Pais by Fernando Garavito, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Helen Lane's French copy of State of Siege, with her notes in text and laid in, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Excerpts from Helen Lane's translation of Santa Evita, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Helen Lane's publication contracts and correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - Helen Lane's obituary, estate papers, correspondence about her death, 2002-2005 (Box 3)
- V. CHARLES GREENLEAF BELL
  - Galway Kinnell typescript of "The River" with his revisions in ink, undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence concerning Charles Bell, 2005-2007 (Box 3)
- Oversize 1
  - Award for "Professional Achievement" inscribed to Helen R. Lane, 1983 (Oversize 1)